Guide to the George R. Van Namee Scrapbooks
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George R. Van Namee Scrapbooks
1918-1945.
Van Namee, George Rivet.
6.25 linear ft. (15 custom boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1452
7932411
Fifteen scrapbooks of news-clippings and political ephemera related to New York politics and the career of New York Governor and Democratic Presidential nominee Alfred E. Smith.
Biographical Note
George R. Van Namee was born in Watertown, New York on December 23, 1877. He graduated from the Cornell University College of Law in 1901 and practiced law in Watertown for nine years before being appointed Clerk of the New York State Assembly from 1911-1913. Van Namee then served as Commissioner of the Bill Drafting Commission, which assists legislators, from 1914 to 1918, after which he worked as Secretary to Governor Alfred E. Smith beginning in 1920. Van Namee's relationship with Smith continued for the rest of their careers, with Van Namee serving as Smith's private secretary and then being appointed by the governor as a commissioner of the Public Service Commission in 1924, a post Van Namee held until his retirement in 1943.
Scope and Content
The George R. Van Namee scrapbooks contain fifteen volumes relating to Van Namee's marriage and later life, New York politics, and especially the career of Alfred E. Smith. The collection is arranged into three series.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series I: General Scrapbooks
Series II: 1928 Campaign Scrapbooks
Series III: Ephemera and Miscellanea
Subjects
Democratic Party (N.Y.); Tammany Hall.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano),--1882-1945.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel,--1873-1944.; Walker, James John,--1881-1946.; New York (N.Y.)--Politics and government--1898-1951.; Campaign literature--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
John T. Steinbock Gift 05/18/2010 2009.2010.M120
- Series I: General Scrapbooks
  This series covers Van Namee’s relationship with Alfred E. Smith, containing clippings, ephemera, and photographs from 1918 through 1945. Included are articles about Smith’s tenure as governor, Smith’s 1928 Presidential run, and details of Smith’s later life and marriage. Also included are photographs and letters from Van Namee’s own life, including his marriage to Rose Fallon, a successful florist, and his appointment and tenure as New York’s Public Service Commissioner. Articles and ephemera from other events of the period--such as articles about Hitler’s death, tickets from the New York World’s Fair, and programs from racing and boxing events--are included throughout. Items relevant to Tammany Hall, Mayor Jimmy Walker, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Pope Pius XI, and New York Irish Catholics are also present.
  - Vol. 1, 1926-1935 (Box 1)
    (News clippings related to Al Smith’s tenure as governor and his Presidential campaign; letter from FDR to Van Namee; Van Namee’s wedding; Van Namee’s trips to Europe; material concerning Mayor Jimmy Walker)
  - Vol. 2, 1918-1920 (Box 2)
    (News clippings related to Al Smith’s first election as Governor; Van Namee’s nomination as Public Service Commissioner; letters of congratulation for appointment)
  - Vol. 3, 1919-1925 (Box 3)
    (Clippings, mostly about Smith’s second election as Governor and about New York City politics)
  - Vol. 4, 1920-1928 (Box 4)
    (Clippings about Al Smith’s second tenure as governor; photos of Van Namee vacations; pamphlets and clippings regarding Smith’s 1928 presidential run)
  - Vol. 5, 1927-1932 (Box 5)
    (Clippings and pamphlet literature from Smith’s 1928 presidential run and its aftermath; Van Namee vacation photos)
  - Vol. 6, 1938-1940 (Box 6)
    (Clippings regarding the death of Pope Pius XI, lead up to WWII, New York politics, Van Namee trips to Europe in 1938 and 1939)
  - Vol. 7, 1940-1945 (Box 7)
    (Clippings related to WWII, Hitler’s death, Al Smith’s death and funeral, Van Namee’s retirement)
- Series II: 1928 Campaign Scrapbooks
  The second series contains six scrapbooks devoted to Smith’s 1928 presidential campaign. Two of these contain printed matter published by Smith’s campaign, such as posters, promotional pamphlets, and transcripts of Smith’s speeches. The other four scrapbooks contain extensive clippings from nearly all American newspapers during the campaign, covering topics that range from the controversy surrounding Smith’s Catholicism to his debates with Herbert Hoover over economic policy and public education.
  - Scrapbook of pro-Smith political pamphlets from Smith’s 1928 presidential campaign. (Box 8)
  - Second scrapbook of pro-Smith political pamphlets from Smith’s 1928 presidential run, with index. (Box 9)
    (Labeled ‘Miss Moran’ on front)
  - First Scrapbook of news coverage and commentary related to the 1928 presidential election (Box 10)
  - Second scrapbook of news coverage and commentary related to the 1928 presidential election (Box 11)
    (Labeled vol. 2 on spine)
  - Third Scrapbook of news coverage and commentary related to the 1928 presidential election (Box 12)
  - Fourth Scrapbook of news coverage and commentary related to the 1928 presidential election, labeled Oct 23, 1928 - Nov 10, 1928 (Box 13)
- Series III: Ephemera and Miscellanea
  The third series contains two scrapbooks of ephemera. One covers the year 1932 exclusively, with material relating to the Great Depression, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, and Van Namee’s own activities in New York. The final scrapbook contains a wide variety of valuable ephemera, mostly relating to New York Democratic politics. Materials are wide ranging and include items like the key to Tammany Hall, dinner invitations to the Manhattan Club, and brochures and tickets from the 1928 and 1932 Democratic National Conventions.
  - Box of Tammany and Van Namee related ephemera, including key to Tammany Hall, photographs, and dinner invitations (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook covering events during the year 1932 (Box 15)